<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>

<articleinfo>
<title>Basic Debugging in Perl 5</title>
<authorgroup>
<author>
<firstname>Steven</firstname>
<surname>Schubiger</surname>
</author>
</authorgroup>
<pubdate>2026-06-13</pubdate>
<abstract>
<para>
This article presents practical methods for debugging Perl programs,
including diagnostic output and the built-in Perl debugger. It
demonstrates how to inspect variables, trace program execution, and
identify runtime errors in Perl applications.
</para>
</abstract>
<keywordset>
<keyword>Debugging</keyword>
<keyword>Basic Debugging</keyword>
<keyword>Perl</keyword>
<keyword>Perl 5</keyword>
<keyword>print statements</keyword>
<keyword>Data::Dumper</keyword>
<keyword>CGI::Carp</keyword>
<keyword>built-in debugger alias -d</keyword>
</keywordset>
</articleinfo>

<para>Copyright (c) 2005-2011, 2015-2016, 2024-2026 Steven Schubiger</para>
<para>
Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3
or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover
Texts.  A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
Free Documentation License".
</para>

<sect1>
<title>print statements</title>

<para>
As the most intuitive debugging facility to the one becoming acquainted with
Perl will likely be first print statements. Such statements may print either
simply debugging hints, contents of variables or anything part of a valid print
expression while the program is being executed. In order to interrupt the
execution of code (what is commonly known as a breakpoint in "proper"
debugging) the Perl program may also wait for random input by the user.
</para>

<para>
Imagine we were receiving a result from complex mathematical calculations and
somehow it failed our expectations; unfortunately, we have already been spending
time proofreading our code for semantical errors and did not come across any or
have overlooked their subtle occurrences.
</para>

<para>So, let us say, <command>$result</command> contains one result that failed our expectations.</para>

<para>By inserting the following statement</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
print "$result\n";
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>the value of <command>$result</command> is printed at runtime with a newline appended.</para>

<para>
This may suffice in normal cases where we do not have much data printed, but it will
fail perhaps if it is vice-versa where the output flow is too fast to be followed
by the human eye. As previously mentioned, in such cases, we will have to interrupt.
</para>

<para>We will extend our single statement to following ones</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
print "$result\n";
&lt;STDIN&gt;;
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
<command>$result</command> is being printed as before, no change introduced here;
we do interfere now by forcing it to wait for input by the user reading from the
standard input. This mostly makes sense for interactive terminal uses, but not so
much for a CGI script, however.
</para>

<para>
An useful and basic feature most debuggers ship with as do most "equivalent" editors
is marking the line one is stepping at or editing by printing the line number at
the left. If we would like to emulate this feature, we could use <command>__LINE__</command>
(which although is a literal, represents the line number of the source on which it
occurs).
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
print __LINE__ . ":\t$result\n";
&lt;STDIN&gt;;
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
The line number followed by a colon will be printed including the interpolated
variable separated by a tab space.
</para>

<para>
It is common for many compilers to state unambiguously with <command>&lt;FILE:LINE: error&gt;</command>
kind of error messages where the programmer has to overlook the source again in case
of an error.
</para>

<para>
We could emulate this feature by prepending <command>__FILE__</command>
(which contains the filename of the current source file being executed).
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
print __FILE__ . ':' . __LINE__ . ":\t$result\n";
&lt;STDIN&gt;;
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
Noteworthy addition: instead of using <command>print</command>, there are
some alternatives which follow below.
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
say $result;    # same as: print "$result\n";
warn $result;   # prints $result as warning to STDERR
</programlisting>
</example>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Data::Dumper</title>

<para>
Simple print statements may be suitable as long as no complex data structures,
i.e. nested ones or references are being involved. A disadvantage that goes
along with such statements is that the source is temporarily being polluted,
which requires that we either have a backup handy or manually remove the
statements after debugging with the risk of eventually introducing subtle
bugs when not all occurrences have been purged.
</para>

<para>
<command>Data::Dumper</command> has been a core module since the beginnings of Perl
5 and it stringifies perl data structures for printing as well as for evaling them.
<command>Data::Dumper</command> may be used in old-fashioned function exporting way,
but also in object-oriented one which compared to former one exposes more methods.
</para>

<para>The following excerpt loads <command>Data::Dumper</command> at compile-time
and prints the result from calling <command>Dumper($result)</command> to the
standard output.</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
use Data::Dumper;

...

print Dumper($result);
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>Examine the output of a more complex data structure, for example:</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
use Data::Dumper;

...

$results = [ $calc, { result1 => $calc ** 2, result2 => $calc * 3 } ];

$d = Data::Dumper->new($results);

print $d->Dump;
</programlisting>
</example>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>CGI::Carp</title>

<para>
<command>CGI::Carp</command> is a module that redirects CGI script warnings and errors
to the browser or a log, making debugging easier. Following examples are not exhaustive,
but should provide a rough overview of <command>CGI::Carp</command>.
</para>

<para>Shows fatal errors in the browser:</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
use CGI::Carp qw(fatalsToBrowser);

die "fatal error";
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>Shows warnings in the browser:</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
use CGI::Carp qw(warningsToBrowser);

warn "warning";
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>Shows fatal errors and warnings in the browser:</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
use CGI::Carp qw(fatalsToBrowser warningsToBrowser);

warn "warning";
die "fatal error";
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>Logs errors to a custom file:</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
use CGI::Carp qw(carpout);

open my $fh, '>>', '/tmp/cgicarp.log' or die "Cannot open logfile: $!";
carpout($fh);

warn "redirected to logfile";
</programlisting>
</example>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>built-in debugger alias <command>-d</command></title>

<para>
perl invoked in the command-line with the <command>-d</command> switch
will launch the debugger. The most essential command is <command>h</command>,
which prints the summary of commands - the equivalent to <command>--help</command>
in many programs with gnuish long arguments. <command>h h</command> lists an even
more extended summary.
</para>

<para>
It is important to become aware of that the Perl debugger, unlike the GNU
C debugger (gdb), assumes implicitly a given breakpoint at line 1 regardless
whether we choose to "step" by saying step <command>(s)</command> or next
<command>(n)</command>. The number in the angle brackets of <command>__DB&lt;1&gt;_</command>
does not, as one could be tempted to believe, indicate which line of source we are stepping at:
it functions as a counter of how many operations have been performed (except <command>h</command>)
since start-up.
</para>

<para>
As mentioned above, <command>s</command> or <command>n</command> are two variants
to step within code: former steps one line and enters subroutines (i.e. subs)
whenever one appears, whereas latter one skips subs by stepping over them.
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
__DB&lt;1&gt;_ s                     # step line, entering subs

__DB&lt;1&gt;_ n                     # step line, skipping subs
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
Given that we do approximately know where a flaw was introduced, we can set a breakpoint
on a line or sub by entering, for example, <command>b 13</command>, which will break at
line 13 if we force the debugger to run through the code via <command>c [ln|sub]</command>
(continue) until the first breakpoint (e.g. line 13) occurs.
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
__DB&lt;1&gt;_ b 13                  # set breakpoint at line 13

__DB&lt;1&gt;_ c                     # continue until first breakpoint reached
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
In case a function or method associated with a foreign class/package gets called,
it could take up a specific extended amount of time for it to return; <command>r</command>
will enforce early returnment from the current subroutine being executed.
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
__DB&lt;1&gt;_ r                     # return from current subroutine
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
All these operations would probably not suffice, if we could not examine variables to
see whether they hold the expected data or not. The most basic operation concerning
data output is <command>p expr</command> which will print the expression supplied.
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
 __DB&lt;1&gt;_ p $result            # print data in $result
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
Assuming we would lose orientation where execution has already progressed to, we could regain
control by either typing <command>.</command> for the current line or <command>-</command>
for the previous one to be displayed. If we choose to view around our current line,
<command>v</command> is suited therefore.
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
__DB&lt;1&gt;_ .                     # print current line

__DB&lt;1&gt;_ -                     # print previous line

__DB&lt;1&gt;_ v                     # view around line
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
Sometimes it will be of use to have an automatic action executed whenever execution reaches
a certain line in the source.
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
__DB&lt;1&gt;_ a 2 p line2           # set action which will be executed before entering line 2

__DB&lt;1&gt;_ A ln|*                # delete an/all action(s)

__DB&lt;1&gt;_ L                     # list all breakpoints, actions, watch expressions
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
localtime() is context-sensitive: it returns in scalar context the current time in
readable format, whereas in list context a list is populated with time entries.
List context evaluation may be enforced by <command>x</command>.
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
__DB&lt;1&gt;_ p scalar localtime    # print time in readable format

__DB&lt;1&gt;_ x localtime           # print indexed elements of list returned by localtime
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
The variables of a certain package can be listed via <command>V package</command>;
an optional pattern may be provided to list a selection of variables only. Module
versions may be displayed by <command>M</command>. <command>i class</command>
allows for insight into the inheritance tree of a class.
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
__DB&lt;1&gt;_ V [package]           # list all variables or of a certain package

__DB&lt;1&gt;_ M                     # show module versions

__DB&lt;1&gt;_ i class               # display class inheritance tree
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
A well-known feature to a frequent shell user is the redo feature which relieves from the
necessity of retyping previous commands; a command may be redone by typing a <command>!
</command> followed by an <command>integer</command>. A positive integer will be added
to the start of the history list to pick a command, whereas a negative one has the
effect of "looking" back.
</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
 __DB&lt;1&gt;_ !1                   # redo first command

 __DB&lt;1&gt;_ !-1                  # redo last command
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>When execution comes to an end, the code may be rerun by <command>R</command>.</para>

<example>
<title></title>
<programlisting>
 __DB&lt;1&gt;_ R                    # attempt a restart
</programlisting>
</example>

</sect1>
</article>
